Well, if you only focus on your brightest students, you know what happens is disparities grow, and you can see this bubble moving slightly to the other direction, but still, an impressive improvement. A major overhaul of Poland's education helped to dramatically reduce between variability among schools, turn around many of the lowest-performing schools, and raise performance by over half a school year. And you can see other countries as well. Portugal was able to consolidate its fragmented school system, raise quality and improve equity, and so did Hungary. So what you can actually see, there's been a lot of change. And even those people who complain and say that the relative standing of countries on something like PISA is just an artifact of culture, of economic factors, of social issues, of homogeneity of societies, and so on, these people must now concede that education improvement is possible. You know, Poland hasn't changed its culture. It didn't change its economy. It didn't change the compositions of its population. It didn't fire its teachers. It changed its education policies and practice. Very impressive. And all that raises, of course, the question: What can we learn from those countries in the green quadrant who have achieved high levels of equity, high levels of performance, and raised outcomes? And, of course, the question is, can what works in one context provide a model elsewhere? Of course, you can't copy and paste education systems wholesale, but these comparisons have identified a range of factors that high-performing systems share. Everybody agrees that education is important. Everybody says that. But the test of truth is, how do you weigh that priority against other priorities? How do countries pay their teachers relative to other highly skilled workers? Would you want your child to become a teacher rather than a lawyer? How do the media talk about schools and teachers? Those are the critical questions, and what we have learned from PISA is that, in high-performing education systems, the leaders have convinced their citizens to make choices that value education, their future, more than consumption today. And you know what's interesting? You won't believe it, but there are countries in which the most attractive place to be is not the shopping center but the school. Those things really exist. But placing a high value on education is just part of the picture. The other part is the belief that all children are capable of success. You have some countries where students are segregated early in their ages. You know, students are divided up, reflecting the belief that only some children can achieve world-class standards. But usually that is linked to very strong social disparities. If you go to Japan in Asia, or Finland in Europe, parents and teachers in those countries expect every student to succeed, and you can see that actually mirrored in student behavior. When we asked students what counts for success in mathematics, students in North America would typically tell us, you know, it's all about talent. If I'm not born as a genius in math, I'd better study something else. Nine out of 10 Japanese students say that it depends on my own investment, on my own effort, and that tells you a lot about the system that is around them. In the past, different students were taught in similar ways. High performers on PISA embrace diversity with differentiated pedagogical practices. They realize that ordinary students have extraordinary talents, and they personalize learning opportunities. High-performing systems also share clear and ambitious standards across the entire spectrum. Every student knows what matters. Every student knows what's required to be successful. And nowhere does the quality of an education system exceed the quality of its teachers. High-performing systems are very careful in how they recruit and select their teachers and how they train them. They watch how they improve the performances of teachers in difficulties who are struggling, and how they structure teacher pay. They provide an environment also in which teachers work together to frame good practice. And they provide intelligent pathways for teachers to grow in their careers. In bureaucratic school systems, teachers are often left alone in classrooms with a lot of prescription on what they should be teaching. High-performing systems are very clear what good performance is. They set very ambitious standards, but then they enable their teachers to figure out, what do I need to teach to my students today? The past was about delivered wisdom in education. Now the challenge is to enable user-generated wisdom. High performers have moved on from professional or from administrative forms of accountability and control -- sort of, how do you check whether people do what they're supposed to do in education -- to professional forms of work organization. They enable their teachers to make innovations in pedagogy. They provide them with the kind of development they need to develop stronger pedagogical practices. The goal of the past was standardization and compliance. High-performing systems have made teachers and school principals inventive. In the past, the policy focus was on outcomes, on provision. The high-performing systems have helped teachers and school principals to look outwards to the next teacher, the next school around their lives. And the most impressive outcomes of world-class systems is that they achieve high performance across the entire system. You've seen Finland doing so well on PISA, but what makes Finland so impressive is that only five percent of the performance variation amongst students lies between schools. Every school succeeds. This is where success is systemic. And how do they do that? They invest resources where they can make the most difference. They attract the strongest principals into the toughest schools, and the most talented teachers into the most challenging classroom. Last but not least, those countries align policies across all areas of public policy. They make them coherent over sustained periods of time, and they ensure that what they do is consistently implemented. Now, knowing what successful systems are doing doesn't yet tell us how to improve. That's also clear, and that's where some of the limits of international comparisons of PISA are. That's where other forms of research need to kick in, and that's also why PISA doesn't venture into telling countries what they should be doing. But its strength lies in telling them what everybody else has been doing. And the example of PISA shows that data can be more powerful than administrative control of financial subsidy through which we usually run education systems. You know, some people argue that changing educational administration is like moving graveyards. You just can't rely on the people out there to help you with this. (Laughter) But PISA has shown what's possible in education. It has helped countries to see that improvement is possible. It has taken away excuses from those who are complacent. And it has helped countries to set meaningful targets in terms of measurable goals achieved by the world's leaders. If we can help every child, every teacher, every school, every principal, every parent see what improvement is possible, that only the sky is the limit to education improvement, we have laid the foundations for better policies and better lives. Thank you. (Applause)
Bien, si solo se enfocan en sus estudiantes más brillantes, sabrán que crecerán las disparidades, y verán mover esta burbuja ligeramente en la otra dirección, pero aún, una mejora impresionante. Una revisión importante en la educación polaca ayudó drásticamente a reducir la variabilidad entre las escuelas, mejorando muchas escuelas de menor desempeño subiendo el desempeño en más de medio año escolar. Y pueden ver otros países también. Portugal pudo consolidar su sistema escolar fraccionado, subir la calidad y mejorar la equidad, y lo mismo Hungría. Así que lo que ven es un gran cambio. E incluso aquellos que se quejan y dicen que la posición relativa de los países en algo como PISA es solo un artefacto de la cultura, de factores económicos, de temas sociales, de homogenización de las sociedades, etc., esas personas tienen ahora que reconocer que la mejora de la educación es posible. Polonia no ha cambiado su cultura. No ha cambiado su economía. No ha cambiado la composición de su población. No ha despedido a sus profesores. Ha cambiado sus políticas y sus prácticas educativas. Muy impresionante. Y todo esto, por supuesto, nos lleva a la pregunta: ¿Qué podemos aprender de estos países del cuadrante verde que han logrado estos altos niveles de equidad, altos niveles de desempeño y subido los resultados? Y, por supuesto, la pregunta es, ¿puede, lo que funciona en un contexto, ser un modelo en otro país? Claro, no se puede copiar y pegar un sistema educativo a ciegas, pero estas comparaciones han identificado una gama de factores que comparten los sistemas de alto desempeño. Todos concuerdan en que la educación es importante. Todos dicen eso. Pero la prueba de verdad es, ¿cómo se valora esta prioridad contra otras prioridades? ¿Cómo pagan los países a sus profesores en relación con otros trabajadores altamente calificados? ¿Te gustaría que tu hijo fuera profesor en lugar de abogado? ¿Cómo hablan los medios de las escuelas y de los profesores? Son preguntas críticas y lo que hemos aprendido de PISA es que, en los sistemas de alto desempeño, los líderes han convencido a los ciudadanos a tomar elecciones que valoran la educación, su futuro, más que el consumo hoy día. ¿Y saben qué es interesante? No lo creerán, pero hay países en los que es más atractivo ir a la escuela que al centro comercial. Esas cosas existen de verdad. Pero dar un valor alto a la educación es solo una parte del cuadro. La otra parte es creer que todos los niños son capaces de triunfar. Tienen algunos países donde los estudiantes son segregados muy jóvenes. Son divididos reflejando la creencia de que solo algunos pueden lograr altos estándares. Pero generalmente eso conlleva grandes disparidades sociales. Si van a Japón, en Asia, o Finlandia, en Europa, padres y profesores en esos países esperan que todo niño triunfe, y lo pueden ver reflejado en el comportamiento de los estudiantes. Cuando les preguntamos a los estudiantes qué importaba para triunfar en matemáticas, los estadounidenses típicamente nos decían, todo es cuestión de talento; si no nací genio en matemáticas, mejor estudio otra cosa. 9 de cada 10 estudiantes japoneses dijeron que dependía de su propia inversión, de su propio esfuerzo, y esto dice mucho del sistema que los rodea. En el pasado, a diferentes estudiantes se les enseñaba de forma similar. Los altos desempeños en PISA acogen la diversidad con diferentes prácticas pedagógicas. Se dan cuenta de que los estudiantes normales tienen talentos extraordinarios y personalizan las oportunidades de aprendizaje. Los sistemas de alto desempeño también comparten estándares claros y ambiciosos a lo largo de todo el espectro. Todo estudiante conoce lo que importa. Todo estudiante sabe lo que se requiere para triunfar. Y en ninguna parte la calidad del sistema educativo excede la de sus profesores. Los sistemas de alto desempeño son muy cuidadosos en cómo seleccionan y contratan a sus profesores y cómo los entrenan. Observan cómo mejorar el rendimiento de los profesores en dificultades, y cómo estructuran el pago de los profesores. Proporcionan un ambiente en el que los profesores puedan trabajar juntos para crear buenas prácticas. Y les proporcionan caminos inteligentes para crecer en sus carreras. En un sistema escolar burocrático, se deja a los profesores solos en las clases con muchas indicaciones de lo que deberían enseñar. En los sistemas de alto desempeño está bien claro qué es buen desempeño. Se ponen estándares ambiciosos, pero después permiten que los profesores averigüen qué necesitan para enseñar a sus estudiantes hoy día. En el pasado la educación se basaba en entregar conocimiento. Ahora el reto es posibilitar la generación de conocimiento por parte del usuario. Los países con altos desempeños han pasado de formas administrativas de rendir cuentas y controlar —cosas como, cómo comprobar si las personas hacen lo que se supone que deben hacer en educación— a formas profesionales de organización del trabajo. Le permiten a los profesores hacer innovaciones en pedagogía. Les proporcionan la clase de desarrollo que necesitan para desarrollar prácticas pedagógicas más poderosas. La meta en el pasado era estandarización y cumplimiento. Los sistemas de alto rendimiento han hecho profesores y directores de escuela creativos. En el pasado, la política se enfocaba en los resultados, en proveer. Los sistemas de alto rendimiento han ayudado a los profesores y a los directores de escuelas a mirar fuera al nuevo profesor, la nueva escuela. Y el resultado más impresionante de los mejores sistemas educativos es que logran altos desempeños a lo largo de todo el sistema. Han visto que a Finlandia le fue muy bien en PISA, pero lo que hace tan impresionante a Finlandia es que solo hay un 5 % de variación en el desempeño de los estudiantes entre las varias escuelas. Todas las escuelas tienen éxito. El éxito es sistémico. ¿Y como lo hacen? Invierten los recursos donde pueden marcar la mayor diferencia. Atraen a los mejores directores a las escuelas más difíciles, y a los profesores más talentosos a las aulas más desafiantes. Por último, pero no menos importante, estos países alinean sus políticas a todas las áreas de la política pública. Mantienen la coherencia durante un período sostenido de tiempo y se aseguran de que lo que hacen sea implementado consistentemente. Ahora, saber lo que hacen los sistemas exitosos no nos dice todavía cómo mejorar. Eso también está claro, y aquí es donde están algunos límites de las comparaciones internacionales de PISA. Se necesitan otras formas de investigación, y por eso PISA no se aventura a decirles a los países qué deben hacer. Pero su fortaleza se encuentra en decirles qué están haciendo los demás. Y el ejemplo de PISA muestra que los datos pueden ser más poderosos que el control administrativo del subsidio financiero a través del cual funcionan por lo general los sistemas educativos. Algunos argumentan que cambiar la administración educativa es como mover las tumbas: no se puede confiar en que las personas de adentro te ayuden con eso. (Risas) Pero PISA ha mostrado lo posible en educación. Le ha mostrado a los países que la mejora es posible. Ha eliminado las excusas de los complacientes. Y ha ayudado a los países a fijar objetivos significativos en términos de objetivos medibles logrados por los líderes del mundo. Si podemos ayudar a cada niño, a cada profesor, a cada escuela, a cada director, a cada padre a ver que la mejora es posible, que solo el cielo es el límite al mejoramiento de la educación, estamos sentando las bases para mejores políticas y mejores vidas. Gracias. (Aplausos)